<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter of resolution concerning the doctrines of the Trinity and the Incarnation</title>
            <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1507B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217844</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829487</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829487</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33927</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52613)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33927)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1995:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter of resolution concerning the doctrines of the Trinity and the Incarnation</title>
                  <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>By Stephen Nye.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Printed in two columns.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Divinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Incarnation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:33927:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33927:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Letter of Reſolution concerning the Doctrines of the <hi>Trinity</hi> and the <hi>Incarnation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOU are pleaſed, Sir, to demand of me <hi>the general Reaſons;</hi> why the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> (or as others now call us, the <hi>Socinians</hi>) have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the <hi>Catholick</hi> Doctrines of the <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Incarnation:</hi> in which all other Sects and Denominations of Chriſtians do agree; and contend alſo for them as <hi>Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental</hi> Doctrines?</p>
            <p>'Tis true, Sir, that we are alone, in our Belief or Opinion of but one GOD, or (what is the ſame) <hi>but one who is GOD;</hi> even the GOD and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: And as we are alone, ſo we are <hi>a little Flock:</hi> If our Reaſons were no more conſiderable than our Number, we ſhould be very contemptible to our Oppoſers. The Caſe was once otherwiſe; there is no Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Hiſtorian but has noted the time, when <hi>All the World was againſt</hi> Athanaſius, <hi>and</hi> Athanaſius <hi>againſt all the World.</hi> But it avails very little, that we can ſay, <hi>Fuimus Trees, ſuit Ilium.</hi> And that which you have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of me, is, <hi>What are our Reaſons;</hi> not how it has come to paſs (or by what Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions) we have been reduced to ſo ſmall a Number?</p>
            <p>I anſwer therefore; Our <hi>firſt Reaſon</hi> is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">The Doctrines of the Trinity and Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, have no ſolid or good Foundation in <hi>Revelation,</hi> or Holy Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Stranger in this Controverſy, who hears the Sermons or reads the Books of ſome of our Oppoſers, would think, that the Queſtion between us and the Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans is on their ſide as clear in Revelation, as 'tis confeſs'd to be on ours in Point of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: for this is the Fault with which they continually charge us, that we exalt Reaſon above Revelation; and that we pretend, that a Force, how great ſoever, is to be put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Words of Revelation, rather than we will admit of any Doctrine which is contrary to Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Now, Firſt; 'Tis not true, that we prefer our Reaſon before Revelation: On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, Revelation being what GOD himſelf hath ſaid, either immediately, or by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired Perſons; 'tis to be preferred before the cleareſt Demonſtration of our Reaſon. But becauſe we cannot ſuppoſe, without Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpect and Injury to GOD, to his <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Veracity,</hi> that he has ſo made us that our <hi>Faculties</hi> ſhould be deceived, in what they <hi>clearly</hi> and <hi>diſtinctly</hi> perceive; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe GOD hath in Revelation frequently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to our Faculties, to our Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Reaſon; therefore we conclude, that what is clearly and diſtinctly diſcerned by Reaſon as true or falſe, is ſo. And from thence we infer; that what is falſe in Reaſon, can never be true in Revelation, or by Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. So that whatſoever in Revelation doth ſeem to contradict Reaſon, can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but our Blunder; our unskilful injudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and too cloſe Adherence to the mere Letter and Words of Revelation.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſo true, that we ought to interpret the moſt clear Revelation, ſo as not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict evident Reaſon; that if we neglect this Rule, we ſhall oft times make Revelation contrary <hi>to,</hi> and inconſiſtent <hi>with</hi> it ſelf; as well as <hi>to</hi> or <hi>with</hi> Reaſon: We ſhall be forced (for Inſtance) to ſay, the Lord Chriſt is <hi>a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33927:2"/>Rock, a Way, a true Vine, a Door,</hi> and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty more ſuch <hi>different</hi> and <hi>contrary</hi> things; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Revelation has <hi>clearly</hi> and <hi>expreſly</hi> called him all theſe.</p>
            <p>I deſire therefore to know, Why our Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers take care not to make themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible by maintaining 'tis <hi>a Scripture-Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> that the Lord Chriſt is <hi>a Rock, a Way, a true Vine, a Door;</hi> on the Account that ſuch a Doctrine, though founded on the <hi>expreſs</hi> Words of Holy Scripture, is contrary to Reaſon: and yet have no regard to avoid the Imputation of Folly, Incogitance and Inadvertence, by contending this is <hi>a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Doctrine,</hi> which is no leſs contrary to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and natural Light; even this, that there are three Almighty and Infinite Perſons, and yet but one GOD. No Man ever had <hi>by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or Reaſon,</hi> nor can have any other Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Three Gods, but only this; <hi>Three Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and Almighty Perſons.</hi> Is it ſuppoſable, that GOD ſhould give forth <hi>contrary</hi> Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations of himſelf? that he ſhould teach us by <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> to apprehend one GOD as but one Almighty and Infinite Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and yet command us by <hi>Revelation</hi> to believe, one GOD is Three ſuch Perſons? Or can we our ſelves obey contrary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, or believe contrary Manifeſtations, concerning the ſame thing, at the ſame time?</p>
            <p>This Foundation being laid, we ſay, Three Divine Perſons, an Almighty Father, an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Son, and an Almighty Spirit, diſtinct from both, being <hi>in Reaſon and common Senſe</hi> but the Periphraſis and Circumlocution for Three Gods; ſo that we can have no other Conception of Three Gods, but only Three ſuch Perſons: that <hi>Revelation</hi> which (by Confeſſion of all Parties) obliges me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve but one GOD; can never be ſuppoſed to require me to believe Three Almighty Perſons.</p>
            <p>So alſo, Reaſon aſſuring me, that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion between Infinite and Finite is ſuch, that they can never be commenſurate, or made one and the ſame: That Revelation, or Holy Scripture, which tells me GOD is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite; that <hi>the Heaven of Heavens contains him not;</hi> cannot be interpreted or underſtood as bidding me believe, that a Perſon who is GOD or an Infinite Perſon (and ſuch, they ſay, every Perſon of the Trinity is) can be <hi>Whole and All</hi> Incarnate, that is, united and commenſurate to a finite Man.</p>
            <p>We abide, Sir, by this Argument; here we fix our Foot, never to be removed: that the Inconſiſtence of the Trinity, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation with Reaſon and natural Knowledg, being undeniably evident, therefore thoſe Doctrines can have no real Foundation in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation, that is to ſay, in Holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>But, Secondly, <hi>As</hi> we conſider that though Revelation is to be preferred before Reaſon; and always <hi>interpreted by Reaſon,</hi> for the Cauſes already given: ſo we cannot but profeſs our ſelves ſurprized, that any ſhould have the Confidence to pretend, that there is <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>expreſs</hi> Revelation, on behalf of the Trinity and Incarnation? In the Name of Wonder, what do theſe Gentlemen mean by <hi>expreſs</hi> and <hi>clear</hi> Revelation: do they mean that they have found out ſome Texts, which directly and expreſly ſay, <hi>There is a Trinity of Divine Perſons, who are but one GOD;</hi> or which ſay, <hi>The Son or ſecond Perſon of the Trinity was incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate?</hi> If they have any ſuch Texts to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce; we ſhall grant them, they have an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs</hi> Revelation for thoſe Doctrines. But in very Deed they mean no ſuch thing: but by <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>expreſs</hi> Revelation they mean what was never meant by any but themſelves; nor by themſelves in any other Caſe or Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but this of the Trinity. They mean, the Trinity and Incarnation are provable, by certain moſt remote and ſtrained <hi>Conſequences,</hi> from ſome <hi>ſuch</hi> Texts of Revelation or Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; as either are of <hi>ſuſpected</hi> Authority and Credit in the Original, among the Learned of their own Party; or are denied by the Learnedeſt of their own ſide, to be truly tranſlated, or finally are interpreted by their own principal Criticks, in ſuch manner as Socinians and Unitarians interpret them. What is this but to ſay, that is an <hi>expreſs</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33927:2"/>which is only an harſh and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Conſequence,</hi> framed by themſelves; and that is a <hi>clear</hi> Revelation for theſe Doctrines, which the beſt and moſt knowing of their own Party interpret to a contrary Senſe?</p>
            <p>Perhaps, Sir, you may be a little ſurpriſed at what I here affirm: but ſo it is, and I make challenge to any of our Oppoſers to convict me of Falſhood; that there is no Text of Holy Scripture alledged for the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or Incarnation, which all the <hi>Catholick</hi> Doctors, and ſome or other of the moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerning and eminent Interpreters and Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks of <hi>the Proteſtants,</hi> have not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that <hi>'tis not to the purpoſe of the Trinity or Incarnation.</hi> The Texts that are cited for the Trinity or Incarnation, are either out of the Old Teſtament, or out of the New.</p>
            <p>As to the Texts of the Old Teſtament, the Learned among our Oppoſers (of all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſions) laugh at thoſe that pretend to find the Trinity or the Incarnation, in the Books of the Old Teſtament: 'Tis univerſally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed among the more Learned Trinitarians, that (to uſe the Words of an Author and Book, licenſed by the famous Faculty of the <hi>Sorbon</hi>) <hi>Ex veteri Teſtamento nihil praeter um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras, i. e.</hi> 
               <q>There is nothing urged for the Trinity out of any Book or Books of the Old Teſtament, but mere Umbrages and Shadows. <bibl>
                     <hi>J. Salabert. Haereſ. domitae, par.</hi> 2 <hi>dâ.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Then for the New Teſtament, all the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> Doctors own, what D. <hi>Petavius</hi> (the moſt learned Writer of the moſt learned <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> among them) has thought fit to expreſs in theſe Words. <q>They that would prove the Trinity out of only the Words of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, without taking to their Aid the Churches Interpretation and Authority, <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant plus ſatis, &amp; ſuo artificio vincuntur, i. e.</hi> They ſweat to no purpoſe; and are beaten at their own Weapon <hi>(Scripture)</hi> by their Adverſaries the Socinians and Arians. <bibl>D. <hi>Petav. de Trin. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>ſ.</hi> 9.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proteſtants</hi> indeed have been ſomewhat more careful of ſuch free and general Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgmets; becauſe they know there is no truſting to <hi>Tradition,</hi> and the Authority of the Fathers; on which the <hi>Catholicks</hi> (ſo called) wholly relie in theſe Queſtions. Notwithſtanding, even <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, given up to us, all their Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Strengths. That Text cannot be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, which ſome or other of the Learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have not, either interpreted as 'tis interpreted by Socinians and Arians; or expreſly ſaid, 'twas not intended by the inſpired Author concerning the Incarnation or Trinity, or any Perſon therein. <hi>I demand ſuch a Text of our Oppoſers; and do here profeſs, that if they name it not, 'tis becauſe they cannot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will leave it here with you, Sir, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>this firſt</hi> be not a juſt Exception to theſe Doctrines: even this, that they have no ſufficient Foundation in Holy Scripture, by Confeſſion of the <hi>moſt</hi> and the <hi>learnedeſt</hi> of our Oppoſers; and that being evidently falſe in <hi>Reaſon,</hi> they cannot poſſibly be true in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Revelation</hi> or Scripture.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Second Reaſon</hi> againſt them, is;</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">There has never yet been any Apology or Defence made (nor can be) for the <hi>confeſs'd</hi> Inconſiſtency of theſe Doctrines with Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but what is equally applicable to the <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> or any other abſurd and impoſſible Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Oppoſers being ſenſible, how great a Prejudice 'tis to their Cauſe, that their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are ſo directly contrary to Reaſon, ſo utterly inconſiſtent with our natural Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and congenit Notions; which were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us by GOD to be Teſts or Touch-ſtones, whereby to diſcern Truth from Falſhood: they have therefore turned themſelves all ways, to find a Remedy for this Evil.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sum</hi> and <hi>Force</hi> of what they have been obſerved to ſay, either in their <hi>Books</hi> or <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> is as follows. <q>
                  <p>The Trinity and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation are indeed incomprehenſible My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries: but Almighty God hath a Right to require of us, to believe on his Word what we do not comprehend or underſtand. He has already poſed us with divers Myſteries and (ſeeming) Contradictions to our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Capacities, in finite, viſible and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33927:3"/>ordinary Objects; thereby to prepare and diſpoſe us, to receive with an humble Faith, what he ſhall pleaſe to reveal in his Word, concerning Objects inviſible and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite. Whatſoever is matter of <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>mere</hi> Revelation, is not to be judged by ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Senſe:</hi> concerning ſuch things there is a Neceſſity to acquieſce in Revelation only; how unaccountable and wonderful ſoever they may ſeem. And if Revelation is ſo expreſs and clear concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; that we would believe, were it not for their (ſuppoſed) Contradiction to Reaſon: in that caſe Reaſon muſt ſubmit to Revelation; elſe we fall into the horrible both Impiety and Foolery, of giving the Lie to God, and preferring our Knowledg before his. What is the Union of the Soul with the Body? how do the Parts of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hold together? are Bodies made up of diviſible Parts, or of indiviſible? If we cannot anſwer theſe, and divers ſuch like Queſtions, without involving our ſelves in great Difficulties, and even in Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Why do we wonder, that there may be ſome (ſeeming) Contradictions, in what we are taught about the Divine Nature, or GOD? Which of the Attributes of GOD is not as incomprehenſible, as the Trinity or the Incarnation? Do we comprehend GOD's <hi>Eternity,</hi> by which he poſſeſſes eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, <hi>all at once;</hi> or his <hi>Immenſity,</hi> by which he is <hi>whole and all</hi> preſent in every Point of Space? Can a finite Mind com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend Infinite Wiſdom, Infinite Juſtice, Infinite Power, or ought elſe that is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite?</p>
                  <p>How many have been as confident, that the very Notion of a <hi>Spirit</hi> implies a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction; and that 'tis not poſſible there ſhould be <hi>Antipodes:</hi> as any Unitarian can be; that the <hi>Trinity</hi> is a Contradiction to Reaſon, and the <hi>Incarnation</hi> impoſſible? This ſhould make us cautious and modeſt; it ſhould ſerve to inſtruct us, that 'tis eaſy for us to miſtake our own Shallowneſs, and our Errors, for Impoſſibilities and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions to true Reaſon.</p>
                  <p>Finally, As hot as the Unitarians are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Myſteries,</hi> and <hi>incomprehenſible things;</hi> themſelves, for all that, advance as many and as great, as thoſe which they oppoſe.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>You know, Sir, that I have elſewhere anſwer'd particularly and ſeverally, to all the Parts of this Defence: but here I will be content to anſwer in general; that <hi>what will prove every thing, will prove nothing.</hi> This Defence or Proof will ſerve as well for the Tranſubſtantiation, or any other abſurd and impoſſible Doctrine, as for the Trinity or Incarnation.</p>
            <p>I am reſolved to keep cloſe to <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs</hi> Revelation: therefore our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf having ſaid expreſly, that he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the true Vine,</hi> John 15.1. I maintain that as 'twas certain by <hi>Senſe</hi> to thoſe who converſed with him, that he was a true and very <hi>Man,</hi> ſo 'tis certain by <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> that he was alſo a true and very <hi>Vine.</hi> 
               <q>That any Perſon ſhould be a true Man and yet a true Vine, is indeed <hi>an incomprehenſible Myſtery:</hi> but Almighty God hath a Right to require of us, to believe on his Word, what we cannot comprehend or underſtand. He hath already poſed us with divers Myſteries and (ſeeming) Contradictions, in viſible and ordinary Objects, both of Senſe and Reaſon: thereby to prepare and diſpoſe us, to receive with an humble Faith, what him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhould reveal in his Word. That the Lord Chriſt is a true Man, and at the ſame time a true and very Vine, is a Point of <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>mere</hi> Revelation; and no way knowable by Senſe or Reaſon: therefore as to his <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> Nature we ought to acquieſce in Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, without further Scruple or Inquiry. The Revelation concerning it, is ſo <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>expreſs, I am</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the true Vine;</hi> that to quarrel with this Doctrine, is to give the Lie to God, and prefer our Knowledg before his. What is the Union of the Soul with the Body? How do the Parts of Matter hold together? Are Bodies made up of diviſible Parts, or of indiviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? If we cannot anſwer to theſe and ſuch like Queſtions; without involving our ſelves
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33927:3"/>in great Difficulties, and even in Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions: Why do we admire that there may be ſome (ſeeming) Contradictions, in our Lord Chriſt's being both a Man and a Vine? Do we better comprehend, how GOD poſſeſſes eternal Life <hi>all at once;</hi> or how he is <hi>whole and all</hi> preſent to every ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Point of Space: than we apprehend, how the Lord Chriſt may be both a Man and a Vine? Who can comprehend infinite Wiſdom, infinite Juſtice, or ought elſe that is infinite? but if we do not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend thoſe Attributes, why do we pretend to comprehend the Extent of infinite Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; or to ſay of it, <hi>Hitherto ſhalt thou come, and no further;</hi> thou canſt make a Man or a Vine, but canſt not make an <hi>humane Vine,</hi> or a <hi>Viney Man?</hi> How many have been as confident, that the very Notion of <hi>a Spirit</hi> implies a Contradiction to our Reaſon; and that there can poſſibly be no <hi>Antipodes:</hi> as any <hi>Anti-Scripturiſt</hi> and <hi>Idolater of Reaſon</hi> can be, that 'tis a Contradiction and impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that a Man ſhould be a true Vine, and a Vine a true Man? This ſhould make us cautious and modeſt; it ſhould ſerve to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us, that 'tis eaſy for us to miſtake our own Shallowneſs and Errors, for Impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Contradictions, to true Reaſon. And as hot as ſome (many perchance) be againſt this Scripture-Myſtery, that a Man is both a Man and a Vine; themſelves find greater Myſteries in the ſame Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. 'Tis (for Example) a greater Leap from Finite to Infinite, and from Man to God; than from Man to Vine downwards, or from Vine to Man upwards: whatever Explication will make the former of theſe but <hi>poſſible,</hi> will make either of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two <hi>eaſy.</hi> We ſhall have no Difficulty in apprehending; that a Man may be a Vine, and a Vine a Man; if we can get but the Glimpſe of a Conception, how a Man may be GOD, or GOD a Man; or how there can be ſuch a Perſon as GOD-MAN.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If you tell me, Sir, that this Parallel is ſomewhat too light in ſo ſerious and grave a Queſtion, as that depending between as and the Trinitarians; I muſt intreat you to ſhow me, where I have made a falſe Step: for if I have made none, I muſt take leave to tell you; the Parallel is no more light than the Doctrines which gave occaſion to it. Mean and childiſh Errors are never ſo effectually and ſucceſsfully detected; as by the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar and eaſy Parallels: and he that makes the Compariſon, is not to be blamed; but he or they that gave the Occaſion of it. I think the Parallel I have made, ſerves to ſhow, that we are never to talk of <hi>clear</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation or <hi>expreſs</hi> Revelation, in Excuſe or Defence of abſurd Doctrines; but that 'tis neceſſary to interpret all both <hi>Speech</hi> and <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> in Conſiſtence with common Senſe and our natural Knowledg. In fine, it ſerves to eſtabliſh this Rule; if the Perſon ſpeaking or writing, is fallible, we muſt <hi>try</hi> the Truth of what is ſaid or written, by <hi>Reaſon:</hi> but if he is infallible, 'tis always his meaning, that we ſhould <hi>interpret</hi> what he hath ſaid or written, by that Reaſon and according to thoſe natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Notions, which he hath beſtowed on us <hi>chiefly for that purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I paſs to our <hi>Third Reaſon,</hi> or third Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, againſt theſe Doctrines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">Theſe Doctrines are as little conſiſtant with <hi>Piety</hi> toward GOD; as they are with <hi>Reaſon</hi> and with <hi>natural Knowledge.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Piety</hi> (in proper Speaking) is that part of the Chriſtians Duty, which he owes to GOD. And though the Goodneſs of GOD had divers other <hi>Ends</hi> (Ends reſpecting the <hi>Comfort and Good</hi> of his Creatures) why he was pleaſed to make what he hath made: yet it becomes us to eſteem and regard Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or our Duty and Service to GOD; as the <hi>great End</hi> that we ought to purſue.</p>
            <p>The chief Parts or Branches of Piety, are <hi>Praiſe, Love, Faith, Devotion, Obedience.</hi> Let us ſee what Agreement theſe, or any of theſe, have with the Doctrines of which we are diſcourſing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The reſpectful and thankful Recogniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both in our Minds, and by our Words, of <hi>the Works</hi> of God, and of his <hi>Divine At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes;</hi> is what all Men call <hi>the Praiſe</hi> of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33927:4"/>GOD. But doth he or ſhe thus praiſe GOD, who aſcribe his Works, Creation, Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, Miracles, all providential Acts, to any other Perſon or Perſons beſides him, who is indeed the Author of them? But when beſides this, we give to <hi>the Gods of our own deviſing,</hi> the Glory of all the incommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Attributes, even <hi>infinite</hi> and <hi>underived</hi> Wiſdom, Juſtice, Power and Goodneſs; when we affirm, that in all theſe Properties they are equal to the ſupream <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>GOD of Gods:</hi> what farther <hi>Detraction from his Praiſe</hi> can be conceived, but abſolute A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm?</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the <hi>LOVE</hi> of GOD. How can we love the true God, in ſuch manner as he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, <hi>with all the Heart, and all the Soul, and all the Mind;</hi> if we have, and profeſs alſo to have as much Love for two other Perſons, as for him who is the only true and legitimate Object of our <hi>higheſt Love?</hi> If we conſider that Love which we owe to GOD, in its Cauſes; they are his ſupream <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> and his <hi>Merit</hi> and <hi>Deſert</hi> towards us: if in its Effects they are a Conformity to his Will; a Readineſs, Proneneſs and Deſire to ſuffer the extremeſt Evils, for his Sake and Service. If therefore this Love be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, if it be communicated to other Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, beſides that one to which we owe it: We do <hi>thereby</hi> and <hi>therein</hi> aſcribe to them his <hi>Excellence;</hi> we impute to them his <hi>Merit;</hi> we pay to them his <hi>Dues.</hi> Is it no Impiety, or rather is it not a deadly Wound to true Piety, thus to miſplace the Propenſions of our Minds, the Affections of our Hearts, the Uſe and Service of our whole Man?</p>
            <p n="3">3. I do not ſay, How <hi>lame,</hi> but what a <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> is that <hi>Faith,</hi> that is made up of <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory</hi> Parts; of Propoſitions that deſtroy one another; of ſuch Inconſiſtencies, that in ſaying and affirming one, you (either expreſly or implicitly) deny the other?</p>
            <p>In their Doctrine of the <hi>Incarnation</hi> they tell us; <hi>an infinite</hi> Perſon is <hi>whole and all</hi> united to <hi>a finite</hi> Man. Is not this <hi>a contradictory</hi> Faith? doth it not confound Infinite with Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and make them to be all one? doth it not deſtroy all the Demonſtrations of <hi>Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try;</hi> and thereby contradict both our <hi>rational Faculties</hi> and our <hi>Senſes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> is, in ſhort, this. There are <hi>three</hi> Infinite, Almighty, All-wiſe <hi>Perſons, three</hi> eternal <hi>Beings, three</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely-perfect <hi>Spirits,</hi> and yet but <hi>one GOD.</hi> Is not this a <hi>contradictory</hi> Faith? Doth it not deſtroy our <hi>natural Ideas,</hi> our <hi>congenit Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</hi> For what are three Gods, but three ſuch Perſons: and what is the Idea, Notion or Conception of but <hi>one God,</hi> which is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and congenit to every Man; but <hi>one</hi> Infinite Almighty All-wiſe <hi>Perſon, one</hi> eternal <hi>Being, one</hi> abſolutely perfect <hi>Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the late Attempts of ſome, to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy (in part) theſe Difficulties: you know, Sir, how vain and fruitleſs they have been. Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> ſaith, the three Divine Perſons are only three <hi>Modes</hi> (that is, three <hi>Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications,</hi> or three <hi>Reſpects</hi> of GOD towards his Creatures) and they make one GOD <hi>as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Will and Memory make one Soul.</hi> But this, ſaith Dr. <hi>Sherlock, is both Non-ſenſe and Hereſy.</hi> How doth Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> mend the matter? Why he hath advanced an Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Trinity, which Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> and other Orthodox Men have, in Print, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as <hi>Tritheiſm;</hi> that is, as introducing three Gods; a far worſe Hereſy than <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſm.</hi> And thereupon they tell Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> in Print alſo: <q>That though he hath not been counted a Fool, yet it may become a wiſe Man to change his Opinion.</q> In a Word, they have (in civil Language) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited him to a <hi>Recantation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. How is <hi>DEVOTION</hi> (another princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Inſtance of <hi>Piety</hi>) diſturbed, by ſuch a ſtrange and unaccountable Object of it? De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion is ſenſeleſs and irrational; if the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be adored and worſhipped, be not conceived by it. But ſuch of Neceſſity muſt be the Worſhip and Devotion of Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; if in their <hi>Prayers</hi> they keep to their <hi>Belief.</hi> For they may talk of a Trinity; but themſelves will not pretend, that they can <hi>think</hi> it: they can have no Conception of it, no more than of Words without Senſe. We
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33927:4"/>have ſeen very lately, that thoſe who have indeavoured to make Senſe of this (as they call it) <hi>Myſtery,</hi> or to repreſent it as a <hi>poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and <hi>intelligible</hi> thing; not only accuſe one another of <hi>Hereſy,</hi> and demand a <hi>Recantation,</hi> but are generally diſclaimed by their own Party. The Party it ſelf (if you mean there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the general Body of Trinitarians) are for <hi>a Trinity which no Man underſtands;</hi> or ought to pretend to give other Account of it, than that 'tis an <hi>incomprehenſible Myſtery;</hi> and this Trinity they call their GOD. And thus by their own Confeſſion, that Blame and Repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand which our Saviour gives to the <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> is equally applicable to them; and what he ſaith of himſelf and the <hi>Jews,</hi> is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in the Unitarians: <hi>Ye worſhip ye know not what: we know what we worſhip,</hi> John 4.22.</p>
            <p n="5">5. As to <hi>Obedience;</hi> the laſt part of our <hi>Piety</hi> towards GOD, and the moſt neceſſary: the Obligation to it, and all occaſion for it is wholly taken away, by the Doctrine of the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> and the Superſtruction which Trinitarians build thereon.</p>
            <p>They ſay, GOD <hi>the Son</hi> being incarnate in our Nature, did by his <hi>active Righteouſneſs</hi> fulfil <hi>for us</hi> all <hi>Obedience.</hi> By his Sufferings in this Life, his Death and Deſcent into Hell (which things they call his <hi>Paſſive Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>): He more than exhauſted all that <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,</hi> that is or can be due to Sin. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he did, was (they ſay) <hi>for us;</hi> and his Righteouſneſs was meritorious of Heaven for never ſo many Sinners: and what he <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered</hi> was <hi>in our ſtead</hi> alſo; and one Drop of his Blood was ſufficient to ranſom and thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Worlds from the Demerit of their Sins: that is, from Hell and all other Puniſhments. The manifeſt Conſequences of theſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, are theſe: (1.) Goſpel-Obedience, good Works, (or a good Life) are in us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary and ſuperfluous; ſome of them have ſaid, <hi>hurtful and dangerous</hi> to Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Salvation. (2.) Heaven is ſo much every Sinner's juſt Due and Debt from GOD, without any Amendment or Newneſs of Life on their Parts, that GOD would be <hi>unjuſt</hi> in giving them no more, if more could be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. (3.) GOD ſhould be <hi>unrighteous,</hi> if he puniſh'd Men for Sin, though unrepented of: becauſe we have in Chriſt our Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative, both fulfilled all <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered</hi> and paid a more than ſufficient Price of Redemption.</p>
            <p>The notorious <hi>Decay of Chriſtian Piety</hi> in all Places and Ages, ſince theſe Doctrines have prevailed, plainly ſhows, That theſe are not <hi>ſpeculative</hi> Conſequences only, but ſuch real Conſequences, as do much influence the Practice of moſt Men. One may know and be aſſured, that 'tis theſe Conſequences and this Belief, which bolſters Men up in their wicked Courſes; becauſe theſe are the things that comfort and ſupport ſuch, at their Deaths. The greateſt of Sinners go away with Peace of Mind; on the Reflection and Conſideration of the infinite <hi>Merits</hi> and <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> of <hi>GOD their Redeemer.</hi> They have not, nor can out-ſin his Satisfaction and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, and applying both to themſelves <hi>by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in him;</hi> that is, by believing he me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited and ſuffered <hi>for them in particular:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they depart, aſſuredly expecting of GOD the Rewards that are appointed to only <hi>Innocence and Well-doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray, Sir, deſire your Friends who find Fault with us, for reviving (as they ſay) <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary</hi> Queſtions, to take it into ſerious and impartial Conſideration; Whether Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines that have theſe Conſequences, and alſo are ſuch Hindrances of the other Branches of Piety, ought not to be again (and again) examined, whether they are (or can be) true?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fourth Reaſon</hi> againſt them is this;</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">They have crumbled the Chriſtian Church, into innumerable and unreconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable Factions and Parries; ſo that there is no poſſible way of reſtoring Peace, but by returning to the <hi>Belief</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of the Unity of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next to Godlineſs or <hi>Piety,</hi> the <hi>Peace</hi> of the Chriſtian Churches ſhould be the Wiſh and Indeavour of every Chriſtian Man. But the Doctrines under Conſideration, have ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33927:5"/>divided the Churches called after the Name of Chriſt; that there is no Agreement but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe Profeſſors, who believe there is but one GOD, or but one who is God. The Orthodox (as they call themſelves) are ſo <hi>multifariouſly</hi> divided, that they are not (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) ten of them in a Party. The whole <hi>Mobile</hi> indeed of them go under the common Name of <hi>Trinitarians;</hi> and the Trinity and Incarnation are the general Teſts of Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxy, among them; but this is <hi>an Orthodoxy only of Names and Words;</hi> for in interpreting thoſe Words and Names, I doubt very much, whether there are <hi>ten</hi> of them that are of a Mind. And the Diſſent among them is ſo bitter and unreconcilable, that the <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma's</hi> fly as thick and faſt at one another, as at the Unitarians. As many Parties as they are, each Party is <hi>heretical,</hi> and in a State of Damnation, in the Opinion of all the reſt. Their Diviſions do reſpect ſome of them the Doctrine of the Trinity; and ſome the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation: I will reckon them up as they ſhall occur to my Mind; without regarding that Method which might be given to Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Difference is about the <hi>Fili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> or whether the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father only, or from the Father and the Son? This Quarrel divides them into two great and almoſt equal Parties; into the Church of the Eaſt, and the Church of the Weſt. The Eaſtern Church, that is to ſay, all <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa, Greece,</hi> and the Iſlands of the <hi>Archipelago,</hi> all <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of <hi>Illyricum,</hi> a good Part of <hi>Poland,</hi> and ſome Part of <hi>Hungary;</hi> all theſe maintain, that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> only. But the Weſtern Church, that is, all the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Nations, and all the <hi>Reformed</hi> or <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> contend that the Spirit proceeds from the Father <hi>and from the Son.</hi> There is no Trinitarian but is in one of theſe Parties; and conſequently none of them, but who is an <hi>heretick</hi> and in a State of Damnation, in the Judgment and Opinion of the one Moyety or half of his Fellow-Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians. But becauſe this damning of one another, upon this Difference between them, has been of late ſo confidently denied by Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> and Dr. <hi>Sherlock;</hi> I am obliged to take notice of the publick Declarations of theſe two Churches, againſt one another. The whole <hi>Weſtern</hi> Church, in the firſt Canon of the ſecond general Council of <hi>Lions,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Damnamus &amp; reprobamiss, &amp;c. i. e.</hi> 
               <q>We damn and reprobate all ſuch as preſume to deny, that the Holy Spirit doth <hi>eternally</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the Father <hi>and from the Son.</hi>
               </q> On the other Hand the Eaſtern Church <hi>excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates</hi> as Sciſmaticks and Hereticks all the <hi>Latins</hi> (ſo they call the Weſtern Churches which hold the <hi>Filioque;</hi> or that the Spirit proceeds from the Father <hi>and from the Son</hi>) on every <hi>Holy Thurſday,</hi> and all other princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Holy-days. <hi>F. Simon Crit. Hiſt. of the Religions of the Eaſt,</hi> p. 16, 17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe two mighty Parties are again ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided, into a great many factious Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences. Into <hi>thoſe</hi> (for inſtance) who teach, that but one Perſon of their (ſuppoſed) Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity was incarnate; and <hi>thoſe</hi> who contend that the whole Trinity was incarnate.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Into <hi>thoſe</hi> who ſay, all the Perſons in the Trinity are equal; and thoſe who (on the contrary) aſcribe to <hi>the Father</hi> a Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative and Superiority, above the other two Perſons; a Superiority not only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of Order,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of Dignity,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Into <hi>thoſe</hi> who ſay <hi>the Son</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> hath underived Godhead, or is GOD of himſelf; and <hi>thoſe</hi> that hold he is <hi>GOD of GOD,</hi> that is, deriveth from <hi>the Father,</hi> Being, Life and Godhead.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Into <hi>thoſe</hi> who ſay <hi>the Son</hi> is ſo the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Father, that he is <hi>the Wiſdom by which the Father is wiſe;</hi> and into thoſe who deny this, as little better than Blaſphemy; becauſe 'tis as much as to ſay, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (without the Son) is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>irrational and unwiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. In what Senſe the three Perſons are <hi>conſubſtantial</hi> (that is, have the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or Eſſence, or Nature) doth unrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilably divide them; the Ancients from the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33927:5"/>Moderns, and the Moderns from one another. One Party ſaith, Father, Son, and Spirit, are <hi>generically</hi> (or if you will <hi>ſpecifically</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantial; that is, as three Men are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantial to one another, becauſe all of them partake of the ſame <hi>ſpecifick</hi> Nature, even the humane; or as three <hi>Guineas</hi> are conſubſtantial, being all of them Gold. The contrary Party ſaith, the Divine Perſons are <hi>numerically</hi> conſubſtantial, <hi>i. e.</hi> do all ſubſiſt in the <hi>ſelf-ſame</hi> Subſtance or Eſſence: as Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, Will and Memory, ſubſiſt in one and the ſame Soul.</p>
            <p n="7">7. They diſpute, whether upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation of <hi>the Son,</hi> the Lord Chriſt became two Perſons; or was only one Perſon, whom they call by a compound and <hi>monſtrous</hi> Name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or GOD-MAN. If the latter of theſe, the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God;</hi> if the other, ſhe was only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mother of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Beſides the Diſpute about <hi>the Perſons,</hi> there is a great Controverſy among them, about the <hi>Natures</hi> in the Lord Chriſt. The <hi>Eutychian</hi> Trinitarians ſay, the Lord Chriſt hath but one Nature; the reſt of them (called <hi>Melchites</hi>) affirm two diſtinct Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, an humane as well as a divine.</p>
            <p n="9">9. 'Tis controverted among them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Conſequence of the Incarnation of <hi>the Son</hi> or <hi>WORD,</hi> there followed two <hi>Wills</hi> and two <hi>Actions</hi> in the Lord Chriſt; or on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one Action and one Will? Alſo,</p>
            <p n="10">10. Whether by Virtue of the Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Body of the Lord Chriſt became in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, and exempt from humane Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Paſſions; or not? Farther,</p>
            <p n="11">11. Whether the humane Nature of Chriſt, being perſonally united to <hi>the Son</hi> or <hi>WORD,</hi> were not by Virtue of that Union <hi>Omniſcient;</hi> knowing even when the Day of Judgment ſhall be?</p>
            <p n="12">12. Whether this Propoſition be Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, or on the contrary <hi>the Seed of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> one Perſon of the Bleſſed Trinity hath <hi>ſuffered</hi> for us?</p>
            <p n="13">13. Whether the Son and Spirit have been once <hi>generated</hi> and <hi>breathed,</hi> and that <hi>from all Eternity;</hi> or whether they are <hi>continually</hi> and <hi>always</hi> begotten and breathed?</p>
            <p n="14">14. They all agree, that there are three Divine <hi>Perſons:</hi> but to make this no Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they are divided in explaining what is to be underſtood by the Word <hi>Perſons.</hi> Some ſay, the three <hi>Perſons</hi> are three <hi>Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of the Divine Nature. But theſe agree not; ſome making them to be <hi>Properties</hi> in the ſame <hi>numerical</hi> Nature. Others take them to be <hi>diſcretive</hi> Properties in <hi>the ſpecifick</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Others ſay, the three <hi>Perſons</hi> are three <hi>Modes</hi> of Subſiſtence, or three <hi>Relations,</hi> or three <hi>Reſpects</hi> of GOD towards his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or three <hi>Operations.</hi> Others affirm the three <hi>Perſons</hi> to be ſo many ſeveral or diſtinct <hi>intellectual Beings</hi> and <hi>Spirits;</hi> as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from one another as three humane Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (or three Men) are.</p>
            <p n="15">15. To add now no more. They require us to believe, that <hi>three</hi> Almighty Perſons are but one God: but in what Senſe or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, three ſuch Perſons make one GOD, is not only diſputed among them; but they are here alſo Apoſtates and Hereticks to one another. Some reſolve this <hi>Myſtery</hi> (as they call it) by an Unity or Oneneſs of Affection, Will and Deſign, between the three Perſons: as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeaking of himſelf and <hi>Apollos,</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that planteth, and he that watereth, are one,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.8. Others ſay, the Son and Spirit are one GOD with the Father, by their moſt perfect Subordination or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to him: All three making but <hi>one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> are therefore ſaid to be but <hi>one GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, ſome ſay, the three Perſons are one GOD by their <hi>Emperichoreſis,</hi> or In-being in one another. But others by Empericho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſis, or <hi>being in one another,</hi> underſtand only this, that the Relation of <hi>Father</hi> ſuppoſeth and includeth that of <hi>Son,</hi> and <hi>vice verſa;</hi> and not that by an impoſſible <hi>real In-being,</hi> the three Divine Perſons are as it were <hi>ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> and ſo confounded.</p>
            <p>We have been told by others, that the three Perſons are three diſtinct Minds and Spirits; and that the only poſſible Union of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33927:6"/>Spirits is <hi>mutual Conſciouſneſs:</hi> So that (in ſhort) the three Divine Perſons are one GOD, <hi>as</hi> (or <hi>becauſe</hi>) they are intimately conſcious to one anothers Thoughts and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally,</hi> Some ſay, the three Perſons are one GOD; by their all having the ſame <hi>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical</hi> Eſſence or Subſtance.</p>
            <p>There are, Sir, you ſee, no fewer than fifteen Diviſions among our Oppoſers; each Diviſion conſiſting of two Parties at the leaſt, ſome of them of four or five. So there are in all about <hi>forty</hi> Parties of them; of which incomparably the greater Number are <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>damned</hi> to all the other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties among them. Give me leave to make two Obſervations hereupon.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) The great and common Boaſt of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians, even their <hi>Number;</hi> on the Account of which they preſume to call themſelves the Catholick (or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi>) Church, is merely a Boaſt. It may be (not untruly) ſaid; <hi>They are the leaſt of Parties,</hi> that ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed a Religion. To comprehend this, Sir, you need only ſuppoſe, a Perſon reſolving to join himſelf to their <hi>univerſal</hi> Church, and in order thereto determining upon all the forementioned Heads of Controverſy among them. For by that time he has ſo done, that is, has choſen his ſide in all the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Queſtions: It will be no leſs than a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle</hi> if he finds himſelf Orthodox and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, in the Opinion of <hi>ten</hi> Perſons beſides himſelf; it may be, the <hi>univerſal</hi> Church will dwindle into his ſingle Perſon. For theſe <hi>forty</hi> Parties of Trinitarians are not all of them ſo many viſible and aſſociated Sects or Churches; but divers of them are Diviſions and Hereſies in one and the ſame aſſociated Church: the Members of the ſame Church are in theſe Points divided, and heretick to one another. And the Number <hi>Forty</hi> affords. ſo many <hi>Changes;</hi> that (as I ſaid) perhaps it will be impoſſible to find <hi>ten</hi> Trinitarians, who are intirely of a Mind in all the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Points and Queſtions. This evidently reduces the (pretended) <hi>Catholick</hi> Church or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Church, to a much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible Paucity, than are the Worſhippers of one only GOD; or, as our Oppoſers by way of Jeſt ſometimes call us, <hi>the little Flock:</hi> to which (however) their Father hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>to give them a Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Whereas Trinitarians generally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend; and that as an Argument which ought to end all further Diſpute about theſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; that the Trinity and Incarnation are <hi>Traditions</hi> derived down to our times, thrô all the intermediate Ages, and by all the Churches profeſſing Chriſtianity: theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions among them plainly demonſtrate the contrary. For if the Trinity and Incarnation are <hi>Traditions,</hi> how comes it to paſs, that Trinitarians are in ſuch contrary Tales about them? how is it that not <hi>ten</hi> of them, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not two of them, are in the ſame Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry concerning them? They agree in nothing but the Words <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Incarnation;</hi> and are forced to acknowledg, that thoſe very Words are not only <hi>unſcriptural,</hi> but not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ancient. <hi>Tertullian</hi> among the <hi>Latins,</hi> and <hi>Clemens Alexandr.</hi> among the <hi>Greeks,</hi> were the firſt of Chriſtians, who uſed the word <hi>Trinity:</hi> and for Incarnation, I do not remember it to be ſo ancient.</p>
            <p>But I have often wondred at this Pretence of moſt Trinitarians, that theſe Doctrines are <hi>Traditions</hi> from the firſt Ages of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. On another Account it is this; All the <hi>Criticks</hi> (without excepting one) who have made a Judgment of the Writings of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the firſt 300 Years; and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>which</hi> of thoſe Writings are genuine and uncorrupted, <hi>which</hi> wholly feigned or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways corrupted; I ſay, all the <hi>Criticks</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly make this a Note of Forgery or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, <hi>if thoſe Writings ſpeak any what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly or evidently of theſe Doctrines,</hi> namely, the Trinity and Incarnation, and the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on them depending. If theſe Doctrines were <hi>Traditions</hi> from the firſt Ages, the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er we aſcend in Time, the more expreſs and clear would the Tradition about them be: And in confeſſing that 'tis quite contrary, the <hi>Criticks,</hi> (that is, the more Learned of the Trinitarians) have given up the Pretence of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33927:6"/>
               <hi>Tradition</hi> and <hi>Antiquity,</hi> and make it proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I may ſay unavoidable, that theſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are not Traditions from the Ancients, but Novelties, and Corruptions, and Depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of genuine Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Whereas ſome have indeavour'd to evade this, by ſaying, Thoſe Fathers have made no diſtinct Mention of, or Determination in theſe Points; becauſe they were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted in their times, but afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be diſputed and denied by Men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting Novelty and Singularity. I anſwer, Nothing can be more frivolous or falſe than this Pretext. For, 1. 'tis notoriouſly falſe, that theſe Doctrines were not denied in the times of thoſe Fathers. The <hi>Nazarens</hi> and <hi>Theodotians</hi> are more ancient than any of the Fathers; and yet 'tis well known, nay, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd by all, that thoſe Sects held the very Doctrines that are now called <hi>Socinianiſm.</hi> 2. Admitting there was as yet none (or very little) Controverſy about theſe Points: yet becauſe they are pretended to be the <hi>Eſſentials</hi> and <hi>Fundamentals</hi> of Chriſtianity, ſo that he that denies them, is an <hi>Heretick;</hi> and he that knows them not, is <hi>no Chriſtian;</hi> what can we rationally infer but this, that the Fathers, who have not delivered theſe Doctrines in any of their Writings, neither believed nor knew them; and that they are a part of <hi>the gradual Corruptions</hi> which have ſo unhappily deformed the Church. 3. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting once more, that there was as yet no Controverſy about theſe Queſtions, which is the thing for which theſe learned Men contend, and their only Excuſe on the behalf of thoſe firſt Fathers; yet this makes wholly for the Unitarians. For beſides this Defect, the Fathers and firſt Ages have ſpoken in their Creed, altogether as the <hi>Socinian</hi> Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians now do. The Creed called <hi>the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles (becauſe it contains the true Apoſtolick Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Tradition)</hi> was the only Creed of thoſe Fathers and Ages; it was, as one of them ſpeaks of it, their <hi>Regula Fidei immobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis irreformabilis, i. e.</hi> the unchangable unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Rule of their Faith. But this Creed expreſſes the very Doctrine of the preſent Socinians, and not of the Church; as our Oppoſers themſelves are conſtrained to own. It attributeth the Appellation <hi>GOD,</hi> and the Creation of Heaven and Earth, to only the <hi>Almighty Father.</hi> It deſcribeth the Son as only a Man; declaring his Conception by the Holy Ghoſt in the Womb of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> his Birth, Death, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion into Heaven, without the leaſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation of an eternal Generation from the Eſſence of the Father; or that he or the Holy Ghoſt are GOD. It ſaith no higher thing of them, than it ſaith of the Holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church; I believe <hi>in</hi> the Holy Ghoſt, I believe <hi>in</hi> the Holy Catholick Church: for ſo (all know) this Creed is read in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Greek, and by all the Fathers.</p>
            <p>Is it now, Sir, conceivable, that theſe Doctrines ſhould be (as Trinitarians pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend) <hi>a Tradition</hi> conſtantly preſerved; when their own <hi>Criticks</hi> reject the Works of thoſe firſt Fathers, as certainly ſpurious or forged, that ſpeak any what directly or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitly of the Trinity, and other depending Points and Queſtions; and when beſides their <hi>common</hi> and <hi>only</hi> Creed is undeniably <hi>Socinian?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I deny not, Sir, that the Fathers of the firſt 300 Years, whoſe Writings have been ſuffered to come down to Poſterity, began to corrupt the true Doctrine concerning <hi>the Perſon of our Saviour;</hi> making him to be much greater than he was. From about the Year 150, ſome of them were got into the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, that were afterwards called <hi>Arianiſm</hi> or the <hi>Arian</hi> Trinity. But this I affirm, and all the <hi>Criticks</hi> among the Trinitarians do own it; that <hi>thoſe Fathers ſpoke not of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and of the Points and Queſtions thereon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending, as the Church now doth:</hi> they ſo held a kind of Trinity, as not to deſtroy the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of GOD; or that only the Father is <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>properly</hi> GOD. But this was a Digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>I proceed to our <hi>fifth Reaſon</hi> againſt theſe Doctrines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">They have been partly the <hi>direct</hi> and <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> Cauſes, partly the <hi>unhappy</hi> Occaſions of divers ſcandalous and hurtful Errors and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33927:7"/>
                  <hi>Hereſies;</hi> particularly of thoſe which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the groſs Body of <hi>Popery.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis well obſerved by ſome, that <hi>one Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity (or Error) being introduced, 'tis always the Ground and Occaſion of many more.</hi> This Aphoriſm was never more ſadly verified, than in the Doctrines of the Trinity and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation. For no ſooner were theſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, by the Countenance of ſanguinary and arbitrary Edicts of the <hi>Bizantine</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, become the more general and current Belief of the Churches, but there immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arely broke in after them, that Swarm of abſurd and heretical Doctrines which have no leſs than <hi>ſubverted</hi> the true and primitive Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>firſt-born</hi> of the Trinity was <hi>the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy of the Pope.</hi> A few Biſhops, not a <hi>fifth</hi> Part of the Biſhops of the Catholick Church, having preſumed in the Council of <hi>Nice, Anno</hi> 325, to determine for the whole Catholick Church ſo great a Point as this; that <hi>there is more than one Divine and Eternal Perſon:</hi> they ſent the <hi>new</hi> Creed and Acts of that Council, to the Churches and Biſhops who had not been preſent at it; to be by them ſubſcribed. Hereupon the Biſhops of <hi>Aſia</hi> aſſembling themſelves in about 30 <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial</hi> Councils, rejected the Word <hi>Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial</hi> (or of the ſame Subſtance with the Father) in which the whole Myſtery of <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarianiſm,</hi> and the Streſs of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, does lie: they would by no means admit of this Word. So faith <hi>Marcus Epheſin,</hi> the moſt Learned of the <hi>Greeks. Concil. Florent. Seſſ.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>The Biſhops of <hi>Germany</hi> and of <hi>Belgium</hi> (now the <hi>Low-Countries</hi>) and of <hi>Gaul</hi> (now <hi>France</hi>) and of the three Provinces of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> would not receive the Creed of <hi>Nice;</hi> giving this Reaſon, that the Word <hi>Conſubſtantial</hi> is unſcriptural. So ſaith St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> that great Adverſary of the <hi>Arians</hi> and other Unitarians, towards the beginning of his Book, <hi>de Synod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Biſhops of <hi>Africa</hi> ſeem not ſo much as to have taken into their Archives or Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtries, the Acts, Canons, or Creed of <hi>Nice.</hi> For in the Year 418, in a Conteſt between them and the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> they ſent to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi> for Copies of the Acts of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council. <hi>Concil. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thag.</hi> 6. <hi>Anno</hi> 418.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Nicene</hi> Council being thus refuſed and deſpiſed by all the conſiderable Nations pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſtianity: the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faction of Biſhops began to conſult of a way, how to ſettle their beloved Doctrine by political Arts; and at length they reſolved upon this Expedient.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 347, having got on their ſide the Emperor <hi>Conſtans;</hi> and finding that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Church of <hi>Rome</hi> were thorowly in their Intereſts, they aſſembled in Council at <hi>Sardica,</hi> and there made thoſe famous Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, on which (all learned Men know) the Authority and Supremacy of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> is wholly grounded, and which thoſe Biſhops have ever ſince exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed. They deſigned by theſe Canons, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Biſhops and other Eccleſiaſticks of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Party (now called <hi>Trinitarians</hi>) in their Biſhopricks and other Church-Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and to eject from time to time all <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians.</hi> But theſe <hi>Politicians</hi> were quite out, in hoping for ſuch an Effect: they were ſo far from governing the Catholick Church by thoſe Canons, that they ſerved to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purpoſe, but the inſlaving the Makers of them and their Succeſſors to the Popes of <hi>Rome.</hi> But for a fuller Account, Sir, of this <hi>Sardican</hi> Council (or rather Conventicle) I refer you to <hi>the Acts of</hi> Athanaſius, lately publiſhed, in which the Hiſtory of theſe <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayers</hi> of the Catholick Church is fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Year 431, it was concluded and determined by the Trinitarian Faction, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Council at <hi>Epheſus;</hi> that GOD the Son was truly and properly incarnate in the Womb of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and was <hi>born</hi> of her; ſo that <hi>Mary</hi> was not only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mother of Chriſt,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mother of God,</hi> This blaſphemons and contradictory Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion being once made; immediately they fell to worſhipping and praying to her. If
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33927:7"/>
               <hi>GOD the Son</hi> is to be worſhipp'd and invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, ſhall we turn our Backs on <hi>the Mother of God?</hi> Shall not ſhe be able to help us, at leaſt by way of <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> to whom the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel ſaid, <hi>Thou art highly honoured of GOD;</hi> and who was (as it were) Wife to GOD the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and (in very Deed) Mother to GOD the Son? Father <hi>Simon,</hi> in the <hi>3d</hi> Chapter of the Critical Hiſtory of the Religions of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> ſaith, <q>It is chiefly ſince the Birth of <hi>Neſtorianiſm</hi> (that is ſince the Council of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus</hi>) that ſo much reſpect hath been ſhown to the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </q> He means, ſhe was not ſo much worſhipp'd and invocated, till that Council had determined againſt <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius,</hi> that ſhe is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mother of GOD.</hi> But Father <hi>Simon</hi> will never be able to ſhow, that Holy <hi>Mary</hi> was at all worſhipp'd or pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto, till the <hi>Epheſin</hi> Council had decreed, that ſhe is to be deem'd <hi>the Mother of GOD.</hi> I do challenge him, or any for him, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any Teſtimony of the Ancients for the Worſhip and Invocation of <hi>Mary,</hi> that is ſo ancient as the <hi>Epheſin</hi> Council. This Father ſhould therefore have dealt as ingenuouſly and freely in this Caſe, as is his manner in moſt others; or ſhould have ſaid nothing at all of this matter, but have choſe ſome other Inſtance to confirm what he had to ſay. He ſhould have owned what he knows to be the Truth, that as the Doctrine of the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion produced this impious and ſenſleſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that <hi>Mary</hi> is the Mother of GOD; ſo that Concluſion was the Cauſe of the idolola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical Worſhip and Invocation of her, by the far greater part of Chriſtians; even by all <hi>Catholicks</hi> (ſo called) and by the whole <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3. After <hi>Mary</hi> was worſhipp'd and prayed to, it ſoon became the Cuſtom to pray alſo to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and afterwards to other <hi>Saints,</hi> and reputed Saints. For if <hi>Mary</hi> who (confeſſedly) was but a <hi>Woman</hi> and a <hi>Saint;</hi> though ſhe was Mother of GOD; can help us by her Interceſſion: Why may not others, who were perhaps as great Saints as ſhe?</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Practice of worſhipping Holy <hi>Mary</hi> and other <hi>Saints,</hi> had been but a little while received in the Churches; but it occaſioned the Worſhip of their <hi>Images</hi> and Pictures. For if the Saints are to be worſhipp'd, then ſo too are their Images and Pictures, <hi>with a relative Worſhip;</hi> that is, for the ſake of thoſe whom they repreſent; and ſo that the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>ultimately</hi> terminates, not in the Image, but in the Saint. Even as the Royal Chair, or Throne, is worſhipp'd for the King's ſake, though he be abſent.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Queſtion about the Worſhip of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, was long conteſted in the Church. Thoſe that ſtood for that Worſhip, thought it a very heinous Diſreſpect to our Saviour; that no Honour ſhould be ſhown to his Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture or Image, no more than if it were the Image or Picture of <hi>an Heathen God.</hi> And this was a very common Argument and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, againſt the Oppoſers of Image-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. In anſwer to this, the Fathers of the 7th General Council (<hi>anno</hi> 754) ſaid, <q>There is but one Image or Repreſentation of the Lord Chriſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the Bread given to us in the Sacrament.</hi>
               </q> This Council conſiſted of 380 Fathers. But the contrary Party at length prevailed; and it was concluded, both for the having and worſhipping of Images, and by way of Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port thereto, that the Sacrament is not the Sign, Image or Repreſentation of Chriſt, but <hi>true and very Chriſt;</hi> the Bread and Wine after the Words of the Conſecration (though they agree not, which are the Words of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration) being turned into the the <hi>real</hi> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>'Tis true the <hi>Greeks</hi> uſed not the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(Tranſubſtantiation)</hi> till within this 300 Years, but they uſed equivalent words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſuch like. If any Wonder that ſuch abſurd and contradictory Doctrines, as the <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> and <hi>the real Preſence,</hi> met with ſo little Oppoſition, in the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches; ſuch an one may make theſe two Reflections. Firſt, that thoſe Churches were led as it were by the Hand to thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, by certain Conſequences from the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33927:8"/>Doctrines of the Trinity and Incarnation, thus. There is a Trinity of Divine Perſons, one of theſe was incarnate in the Womb of the Virgin; ſhe is thereupon the Mother of GOD; if the Son of GOD is undoubtedly to be worſhipp'd, then ſo too is the Mother of GOD; if Holy <hi>Mary,</hi> then others who were as much Saints as ſhe; if Chriſt and the Saints, then for their Sakes their Images al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, which are Signs of them. But Chriſt hath appointed the Sacramental Elements, as the only Signs of his Body: This is a Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty indeed: Therefore to defend Image-Worſhip, we will ſay, the Sacrament is not the Sign, but the very Body of Chriſt GOD-MAN. Secondly, it may be farther conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that theſe Churches having already ſwallowed ſo many palpable Contradictions to Reaſon, Scripture, and firſt Antiquity in the Doctrines of the Trinity and Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; they now ſtuck at nothing. It became now the Note and Mark of an <hi>Heretick,</hi> to talk of Abſurdities and Contradictions, in any Doctrine whatſoever; and the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of a Catholick or Orthodox Perſon, if one had no regard at all to ſuch things, but only to help forward the Humour and Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of Superſtition; that is, to believe <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible Tales</hi> about the Saints, and <hi>monſtrous Opinions</hi> concerning GOD, and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Church.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the Holy Scriptures are not a a <hi>compleat Rule,</hi> not ſufficient to direct our Faith and Practice, without the Aid and Help of the Churches <hi>Tradition;</hi> all know is one of the Errors of the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and which they could never yet be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to give up. Ask them, what ground they have for ſuch an Opinion? They an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer as one Man; 'Tis notorious and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable that the principal Articles of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, the Trinity and Incarnation, cannot be proved by only Scripture. They profeſs openly and ingenuouſly, that the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians</hi> have certainly beaten all their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers at thoſe two Weapons, <hi>mere Scripture</hi> and <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Another Birth of the Trinitarian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines is the <hi>Papal Indulgences,</hi> with all that Merchandize of Souls that has followed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. Firſt, and by way of Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is ſuppoſed, that the Lord Chriſt is GOD as well as Man; and that he being GOD incarnate in our Nature, his Righteouſneſs and Sufferings muſt needs be of infinite Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue. Next it is held, that the Sufferings of Chriſt, who is GOD-MAN, and of the Saints, are <hi>the Treaſure which he hath given to the Church;</hi> which Treaſure is to be diſpenſed by his <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car,</hi> even the <hi>Pope</hi> or Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Diſpenſations of this Treaſure to particular Perſons, by the Pope himſelf, or thoſe who are by him authorized, are called <hi>Indulgences;</hi> and have been bought at mighty Rates, by thoſe who thought they had need of them, either for themſelves or their dead Friends.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The laſt of their Paradoxes which I ſhall now mention, and which is common to all Trinitarians, and is (by their own Confeſſion) a neceſſary Conſequence of the Incarnation, is their Doctrine of the <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Holy Scriptures ſay, Almighty God of his Grace and Goodneſs doth pardon our Sins, on the Conditions of Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance on our Parts. The Scriptures are ſo expreſs in aſcribing our Pardon and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from Hell and Damnation, to the Mercy and Grace of GOD forgiving us; that Trinitarians dare not directly deny it ſo to be: but then becauſe they pretend that GOD was incarnate, and ſuffered in our ſtead, they are forced to this Concluſion. That God hath <hi>freely pardoned,</hi> and yet was <hi>infinitely overpaid</hi> for all our Tranſgreſſions and Sins. That of his <hi>mere Grace,</hi> the Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and <hi>Riches of his Grace,</hi> he will <hi>pardon and ſave</hi> the Penitent, becauſe he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived for them <hi>a Price of Redemption,</hi> able to redeem as many Worlds; as he is pleaſed to pardon or ſave particular Sinners.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Branches growing upon the <hi>Trinitarian</hi> Stock; theſe the Fruits of that Tree: But ſuch as the Fruits or Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of theſe Doctrines have been, ſuch alſo was their Original and Extraction; as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33927:8"/>we ſhall ſee in the next, which is our <hi>ſixth Reaſon</hi> or Exception againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">They are of <hi>Paganick</hi> or <hi>Heathen</hi> Deſcent and Original, and were introduced into the Church by the <hi>Platonick</hi> Philoſophers, when they came over to Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of our Diſputes with the Trinitarians is concerning the Original of theſe Doctrines, from whom they are derived, or by whom they were invented? He that is generally (and indeed deſervedly) confeſs'd to have written the moſt learnedly on this Subject, is D. <hi>Cudworth,</hi> in the <hi>Intellectual Syſtem.</hi> The Sum of what he ſaith, up and down, in that large Book in behalf of the Trinity, is this, <q>The Chriſtian Trinity is the very ſame with the Trinity of the <hi>Platonick</hi> Philoſophers: Yet we are not to think, that the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> were the firſt Authors or Deviſers of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: <hi>Plato</hi> learned it of <hi>Parmenides, Parme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nides</hi> of the <hi>Pythagoreans, Pythagoras</hi> from <hi>Orpheus</hi> and the Books of <hi>Egyptian Hermes,</hi> and other. <hi>Hermaic</hi> Books, which Books contained the Arcane Theology of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians.</hi> The <hi>Magisk</hi> or <hi>Chalday</hi> Oracles, and the <hi>Mithraick</hi> Myſteries, both of them derived from <hi>Zoroaſter</hi> (a moſt ancient and ſage King of the <hi>Bactrians</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi>) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs alſo the Myſtery of the Trinity. The <hi>Romans</hi> had their <hi>Capitoline</hi> Trinity, which they derived from the <hi>Phrygians,</hi> they from the <hi>Samothracians.</hi> This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Philoſophers and Nations makes it more than probable, and no leſs than cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that the Trinity was no humane In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, <hi>for how ſhould ſo many jump in the ſame groundleſs Conceit;</hi> but a Theology of Divine Original, even a Part of the <hi>Cabala</hi> Tradition or oral Law of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which they had from<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> and he from GOD, which alſo is the Opinion of <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Theodoret,</hi> the ableſt Hiſtorians and Antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Primitive Church.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To make up weight I will fling into the Scale three Authorities, altogether as conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable and authentick, as any of theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by Dr. <hi>Cudworth.</hi> Let them take the <hi>Grecian</hi> Trinity, which is much older than the <hi>Roman, Phrygian</hi> or <hi>Samothracian:</hi> Let them take the Books of <hi>Hyſtaſpes,</hi> another moſt ancient and ſage King of the <hi>Medes;</hi> which Books are celebrated by <hi>Lactantius,</hi> and other Fathers. We will alſo give them the <hi>Sybillin</hi> Oracles or Verſes, which ſpeak ſo expreſly of the Father, Son, and Spirit, and even of the Incarnation, that no <hi>Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> or <hi>Arian</hi> can deliver himſelf more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitly or evidently.</p>
            <p>He ſaith, <q>How ſhould ſo many Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers and Nations jump in the ſame ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Conceit? Therefore the Trinity is a part of the Jewiſh <hi>Cabala</hi> or Oral Law, and was from them borrowed by other Nations, and by the Philoſophers.</q> I omit that the Nations and Philoſophers by him mentioned are but few: But all Men know, there was an incomparably greater Conſent of Nations and Philoſophers in Polytheiſm, or <hi>the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment and Worſhip of many diſtinct Gods.</hi> And that Conſideration ſhould have made this learned Author aware, that a ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Conſent of <hi>many</hi> is not always the Effect of <hi>a divine Tradition,</hi> but too often of <hi>a dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical Suggeſtion,</hi> or other Cauſes.</p>
            <p>Again, ſuppoſing the aforeſaid Conſent of Philoſophers and Nations; yet 'tis very odly father'd by a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Divine, on a <hi>Cabala</hi> Tradition or Oral Law of the <hi>Jews.</hi> 'Tis one of the Principles of us Proteſtants, to diſclaim all (pretended) <hi>Cabala's</hi> and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, whether of <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and to believe there never was any other Divine Tradition, but only the Books of the Old and New Teſtaments.</p>
            <p>I am ready to diſpute this Point at large with any of our Oppoſers, whenever they ſhall think fit again to inſiſt on it. In the mean time I take notice, that indeed the <hi>Phariſees</hi> having deviſed of their own Heads divers <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Rites;</hi> to give them the greater Authority, they called them Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and pretended they were a <hi>Cabala</hi> or Oral Law, delivered originally by <hi>Moſes.</hi> But the ſounder part of the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, even all the <hi>Karaits</hi> diſown any ſuch Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And our Saviour, whoſe Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33927:9"/>I hope may be equivalent to <hi>Euſebius</hi> or <hi>Theodorets,</hi> calls theſe Traditions and this (pretended) Law, not <hi>a Theology of divine O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal,</hi> but <hi>Doctrines and Commandments of Men,</hi> Matth. 15.6, 9. Nor is there any mention or leaſt Intimation of ſuch a <hi>Cabala</hi> or Law, in any of the Books of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. And it ſeems incredible, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſo many of the <hi>Holy</hi> Writers there ſhould be no where found ſo much as any Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion to their <hi>Cabala,</hi> if indeed they had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged or known of any ſuch thing: Why did not <hi>Eſdras,</hi> when he collected in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one, the ſcattered and diſperſed Canon of Scripture, without omitting the <hi>Proverbs</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and others, or his Book of <hi>Love;</hi> why did he not at the ſame time commit to Writing, and publiſh the Divine <hi>Cabala,</hi> of ſo much more <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Concernment,</hi> than divers Pieces by him publiſhed and added to <hi>the Law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, admitting the (pretended) aforeſaid Conſent of ſome Philoſophers and Nations, and alſo a Tradition, <hi>Cabala,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Law of the <hi>Jews:</hi> yet 'tis certain the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is no part of that <hi>Cabala:</hi> For all the World knows that the <hi>Jews,</hi> though they ſtrictly adhere to their <hi>Cabala,</hi> yet are ſo far from acknowledging a Trinity, that this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is the very Stumbling-block which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders their entring into the Church. That whole Nation, and all the Sects of them, hold the Chriſtians to be Polytheiſts and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, on the Account of the Doctrine of the Trinity. They pronounce Chriſtianity to be a much worſe Idolatry than <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s Calves: Which were not two fictitious Gods added to the true one; but only Images of the <hi>Cherubims,</hi> as the <hi>Cherubims</hi> were Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyfick Reſemblances of the one true GOD. So that though the <hi>ten</hi> Tribes were guilty of a kind of Idolatry, by their worſhipping the true GOD under forbidden Reſemblances, (for though the <hi>Cherubims</hi> themſelves were ſet up by GOD's Order; yet not for Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or to common Sight) they were not <hi>Polytheiſts;</hi> they owned with all the reſt of the <hi>Jews,</hi> but one Divine Perſon.</p>
            <p>I doubt not, Sir, but that you perceive, that the whole Force of Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi>'s Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, from the (ſuppoſed) Conſent of ſome Nations and Philoſophers, is enervated; and that ſuch (pretended) Conſent, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Trinity, is not (as he ſays) <hi>a Theology of Divine Tradition,</hi> but merely and ſolely <hi>of Paganick and Heathen Extraction;</hi> and brought into the Chriſtian Church by the <hi>Platonick</hi> Philoſophers, when they came over to Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>I could now tell you, Sir, that whereas Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi> brings in his <hi>Philoſophers, Oracles, Kings</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi> as believing and aſſerting the Trinity; even in the dark times of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm: this is all <hi>mere Flouriſh</hi> and <hi>Rhodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montade.</hi> For, firſt, as to the Books of <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, Zoroaſter,</hi> and <hi>Hyſtaſpes,</hi> as alſo the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>billin</hi> and <hi>Chalday</hi> or <hi>Magick</hi> Oracles, they are all of them Forgeries, partly of the Jews, a little before the Nativity of our Saviour, partly of the Chriſtians of the ſecond and third Centuries. And this is ſo generally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, and ſo clearly demonſtrated by the <hi>Criticks,</hi> that I was extreamly ſurprized to ſee ſuch Authorities alledged in a Book writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by Dr. <hi>Cudworth,</hi> a Man (if any other) of true and real Learning. But ſo it is, that in the Defect of genuine and ſolid Proofs, the moſt Learned muſt have recourſe to ſuch as their Cauſe will afford. Next, as to the Nations and Philoſophers by him mentioned; the Authors that knew thoſe Nations and Writers, better than at this Diſtance of time we now can; particularly the moſt learned <hi>Plutarch</hi> and <hi>Laertius;</hi> theſe Authors ſay, that thoſe Philoſophers and Nations did not hold a Trinity, but a Duality of Principles or Gods, that is, a good and a bad GOD. And by what they ſay of thoſe Gods or Principles, they ſeem to mean no more than what we are taught in Holy Scripture, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning GOD and that malign (but ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate) Spirit called <hi>the Devil</hi> and <hi>Satan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you will ſay, the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> held a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Divine Perſons. Yes, ſome of them did: I ſay ſome of them; for the more learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Platoniſts</hi> (ſuch as <hi>Jamblichus, Proclus,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:33927:9"/>and <hi>Plato</hi> himſelf) did not think their (ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd) Trinity to be the ſupream GOD; but that over their Trinity there is one moſt ſimple <hi>Monadick</hi> or <hi>ſolitary Being,</hi> who is GOD of Gods, and the firſt Author of all things. If you ask, How the <hi>vulgar Platoniſts</hi> came to ſtumble upon a Trinity? I anſwer; They finding that the firſt Philoſophers had called GOD, <hi>Hen</hi> and <hi>Tagathon,</hi> or <hi>the One</hi> and <hi>the Good;</hi> as alſo <hi>Logos Nous</hi> and <hi>Sophia,</hi> or <hi>the Reaſon</hi> (or WORD) <hi>the Mind</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom:</hi> And finally, <hi>Pſyche, the Soul,</hi> becauſe he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vades and governs the World, as the Soul does the Body: They being the moſt fanci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Enthuſiaſtical of all Men, exceeding the <hi>Quakers</hi> in Enthuſiaſm, and the <hi>Behme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> in <hi>Fancifulneſs</hi> and <hi>Affectation of Myſtery;</hi> miſtook the aforementioned <hi>Properties</hi> of the Divine Nature for Perſons, or wilfully and affectedly <hi>allegoriz'd</hi> them into <hi>Perſons. Hen</hi> and <hi>Tagathon</hi> (<hi>the One</hi> and <hi>the Good</hi>) they made to be the ſame, even the Father and Fountain of the Deity; becauſe all Number proceeds from <hi>One</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> and becauſe <hi>Goodneſs</hi> (as theſe Philoſophers often ſpeak) is better than <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Wiſdom. Nous, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos,</hi> and <hi>Sophia,</hi> (that is, Mind, Reaſon, and Wiſdom) being but equivalent Words, of theſe they made the ſecond Perſon; or (as ſome of them call him) <hi>the Son. Pſyche,</hi> or the Mundane <hi>Soul</hi> was the third; becauſe <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is better than, and ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to all things but <hi>Tagathon</hi> or <hi>Goodneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is, Sir, a certain Fate always at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on Error, by which ſhe is firſt or laſt betrayed and expoſed, even by thoſe who ſeek to maintain and defend her. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi> hath ſpent ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many Sheets in diſcovering a Trinity among ſeveral Philoſophers and Nations more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient than the Platoniſts, yet he hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where unſaid all again, and confeſs'd that the <hi>Platonick</hi> Trinity was nothing but an Affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or <hi>Blunder</hi> of thoſe Philoſophers; and as I juſt now ſaid, either their <hi>Miſtake</hi> or their <hi>Exchange</hi> of the <hi>Properties</hi> of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, for ſo many Divine <hi>Perſons.</hi> His own Words (at <hi>p.</hi> 206 of the <hi>Intel. Syſtem</hi>) are theſe; <q>We have propoſed the three principal <hi>Properties</hi> or Attributes of the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The firſt whereof is infinite GOOD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESS with Fecundity; the ſecond infinite WISDOM or Knowledg; the third infinite <hi>active</hi> and <hi>perceptive POWER.</hi> From which three Divine Attributes and Properties, the <hi>Pythagorians</hi> and <hi>Platoniſts</hi> ſeem to have framed their <hi>Trinity.</hi>
               </q> So at legnth this learned Perſon hath given it up to us, after ſo great Endeavours to prove the contrary, that the Trinity is of mere <hi>Paganick</hi> and <hi>Heathen</hi> Original, the <hi>Device</hi> or the <hi>Miſtake</hi> of the <hi>Platoniſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>laſt Exception</hi> or <hi>Reaſon</hi> is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">As the Trinity, when firſt brought into the Church by the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> did by its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Abſurdity and Impoſſibility, give a Check and Stop to the Progreſs of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; ſo ever ſince it has ſerved to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate <hi>Deiſm</hi> and <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> and to hinder the Converſion of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Mahometans,</hi> and the <hi>Heathen</hi> Nations not yet turned to Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You cannot, Sir, expect in a ſingle Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a large and ample Proof of this Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mine: but however I will ſay here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon enough to convince you, or any other unprejudic'd Perſon, that I am able to make ſuch a Proof of it (whenever it ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by our Oppoſers) as will very much ſurprize the Idolaters of theſe Doctrines.</p>
            <p>For the firſt Part of this Aſſertion, I will now content my ſelf with the plain Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of <hi>Lactantius, Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 29. This learned and eloquent <hi>Father,</hi> diſputing concerning theſe very Doctrines, ſays, <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſe quaerathìc aliquis, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <q>Here ſome one may perhaps ask, How, though Chriſtians profeſs to worſhip but one GOD, yet we ſeem to believe and hold two Gods, GOD the Father, and GOD the Son? <hi>This Doctrine hath been a great Stumbling-block to many,</hi> who confeſs that in other Points of the Chriſtian Doctrine, we ſpeak what is probable and fit to be imbraced, but in this they think we ſumble, that we hold a ſecond GOD, and him alſo a mortal one, or one who could die.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33927:10"/>
            <p>You may pleaſe, Sir, here to take notice, that the Reaſon why <hi>Lactantius</hi> mentions on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two Gods, the Father and the Son; was becauſe the Divinity of the Holy Spirit was not yet believed, or (I think) ſo much as mentioned by any. The Council of <hi>Nice</hi> it ſelf durſt not ſay the Holy Ghoſt is GOD; no, nor the Council of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Terms: For as <hi>Petavius</hi> has noted the Party of the <hi>Pneumatomacht</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> thoſe who denied the Divinity of the Spirit) were yet the more powerful Party in the Church. <hi>D. Petav. de Trin. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>ſ.</hi> 14, and 21. See alſo <hi>Huetius, Origenian. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 2. <hi>ſect.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>Deiſm</hi> and <hi>Atheiſm:</hi> Some (other-ways diſcerning Men) have not Judgment e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to diſtinguiſh between the <hi>corrupted</hi> and the <hi>ſincere</hi> Parts of Religion, but they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the whole of Religion together, and judg it to be all of it <hi>falſe,</hi> or all <hi>true.</hi> From theſe two ſorts of Men proceed all the <hi>Deiſts,</hi> and moſt, if not all <hi>Atheiſts.</hi> The Atheiſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects all Religion whatſoever, for the ſake of ſome unaccountable and abſurd things, which vulgarly paſs for the principal Articles of Religion. The Deiſt, far more judicious, rejects hereupon only all poſitive or <hi>revealed</hi> Religion, and takes up with natural Religion, <hi>i. e.</hi> with the Belief of a GOD, whoſe Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Wiſdom he plainly ſees in the <hi>Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture</hi> and <hi>Contrivance</hi> of the World, and with the Dictates of Reaſon, and our congenit and natural Notions concerning moral and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moral, or good and evil.</p>
            <p>This, Sir, is not a Place to argue either againſt the Deiſt or Atheiſt; I had here only to obſerve, that from the abſurd Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of true Religion, by <hi>injudicious</hi> or <hi>fanciful</hi> Men, have and do ariſe all the Deiſm, and moſt part of the Atheiſm with which our Age is infeſted.</p>
            <p>There is ſo much the more Reaſon for our utmoſt Indeavours, to withſtand the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Progreſs of thoſe two, Deiſm and that Peſt of Atheiſm, by purging Religion of all the contradictory and impoſſible Doctrines which give occaſion to thoſe Miſtakes, becauſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity has already loſt ſo much ground to <hi>Mahometiſm</hi> or <hi>Turciſm. Mahomet</hi> is affirmed by divers Hiſtorians, to have had no other Deſign in pretending himſelf to be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, but to reſtore the Belief of <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of GOD,</hi> which at that time was extirpated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Eaſtern Chriſtians, by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Trinity and Incarnation. They will have it, that <hi>Mahomet</hi> meant not his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhould be eſteemed a new Religion, but only the Reſtitution of the true Intent of the Chriſtian Religion. They affirm more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that the <hi>Mahometan</hi> learned Men call themſelves the <hi>true</hi> Diſciples of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> or Chriſt; intimated thereby that Chriſtians are Apoſtates from the moſt eſſential Parts of the Doctrine of the <hi>Meſſias;</hi> ſuch as the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of GOD; and that he is to be worſhipp'd without Images or Pictures, in Spirit and in Truth. But whatſoever the Deſign of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> was, 'tis certain <hi>Mahometiſm</hi> has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed over greater Numbers and more Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, than at this Day profeſs Chriſtianity: Nay, it has worn Chriſtianity out of great part of <hi>Europe,</hi> moſt of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and all Roman <hi>Africa;</hi> not by Force and the Sword, for the <hi>Mahometans</hi> grant Liberty of Religion to all the conquered Provinces of Chriſtians; but by that one Truth in the <hi>Alchoran,</hi> the Unity of GOD. The <hi>Naturalneſs</hi> of their Belief of the Unity of God, and the unreconcilable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtence of the Trinity with that Belief, make it impoſſible ever to reconcile the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometans</hi> (whether <hi>Turks, Moors,</hi> or <hi>Perſians</hi>) to Chriſtianity. This is that by which both they and the <hi>Jews</hi> are perpetually and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Hope of regaining them, alienated from us, that they ſuppoſe the Trinity to be the Doctrine of all Chriſtians; and from thence conclude, that <hi>modern</hi> Chriſtianity is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nor other than a ſort of <hi>Paganiſm</hi> and <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Nations alſo who are yet <hi>Pagans,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject Chriſtianity for the ſake of the corrupt Doctrines againſt which we are arguing. Of this there has been a calamitous Inſtance in the <hi>Tartars.</hi> This warlike People, who have made themſelves ſo terrible by their <hi>Cavalry,</hi> to the great Kingdoms of <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:33927:10"/>and even to <hi>Germany</hi> it ſelf, were loſt to Chriſtianity by Occaſion of the Doctrines of the Trinity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the Year 1246, Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> IV ſent an Ambaſſage to <hi>Bati</hi> Cham of <hi>Tartary,</hi> inviting him to the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>Bati</hi> received the Ambaſſage civilly; but when he heard from <hi>the Religious</hi> ſent to inſtruct him, what were the chief Points of the Chriſtian Faith, the Trinity, the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the Tranſubſtantiation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He thank'd the Pope for his Kindneſs, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to make no Incurſions into the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Countries for five Years next inſuing; but withal declared himſelf not ſatisfied with the Chriſtian Religion, as repreſented to him. Immediately after the <hi>Saracens</hi> ſent a like Ambaſſage to <hi>Bati,</hi> recommending to him (ſaith the Hiſtorian) <hi>Mahometis ſectam tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàm plauſibiliorem,</hi> i. e. <hi>The more plauſible Sect of</hi> Mahomet: And theſe prevailed, <hi>Bati</hi> and the whole Nation of the <hi>Tartars</hi> ſubmitting to <hi>Mahometiſm,</hi> in which they continue to this Day, and are both the <hi>Shield</hi> and <hi>Sword</hi> of that way of acknowledging and worſhipping GOD. <hi>L. Surius Comment. rerum in Orbe Geſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, Sir, are the Damages ſuſtained by Chriſtianity, by occaſion of theſe Doctrines: I believe by that time you have well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them, you will conclude, theſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines will never repair half the Waſtes they have already made in our Holy Religion; and that they are honeſt Men who are jealous of, and deſirous to inquire very ſtrictly into the Grounds of ſuch <hi>Paradoxical</hi> Perſwaſions as have already given ſuch deep Wounds to our common Cauſe of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>I will conclude, Sir, for this time, with only telling you, that the <hi>Reaſons</hi> I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, might <hi>all</hi> of them have been much <hi>am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified</hi> and <hi>illuſtrated;</hi> and <hi>ſome</hi> of them great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>exaggerated.</hi> But that is a Deſign hardly practicable in a Letter; the Brevity of a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter even conſtrained me to lay before you what I had to ſay in <hi>few</hi> Words, and in a <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>ſincere</hi> Diſcourſe, without the Arts or Pomp of Rhetorick. Nor am I offended at it; for our Cauſe needs not thoſe Helps. Till our Oppoſers can extinguiſh Reaſon and common Senſe in Men; while there are any left who are not wholly Prieſt-ridden, who have not abandoned the Conduct and Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>natural Knowledg</hi> for that of a <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>a Divine Light</hi> for an <hi>Ignis fatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> or <hi>Will-a-wiſp:</hi> So long (I think) we need not be very ſollicitous, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Diſcourſes or Writings concerning theſe Doctrines, be altogether ſo <hi>laboured</hi> and <hi>artificial,</hi> as our Oppoſers muſt take Care that theirs are.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SIR, I am your moſt Obliged and Aſſured.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
